Tenneco Unix team work to do

Dead partition mobility script.

cluster script ( CI )

Update / correct /etc/exports file on all servers. - remove entries that are no longer required for servers and exported files

Document average service times from all unix servers. (sar-d)

Docuemntation (hostname,virtual/phys,vio/vmware,array,application)

Implement cleaning up /home filesystem on NIM post install cleanup script.

Reconfigure Production EDI FTP cluster.

NFS softmount timeout / sshd startup.

Research AD authentication for Unix users.

Enable time synchronization ntpdate in RC scripts or CRON.

Design and implement I/O load balancing on Virtual SCSI guests.

Find out and list mirrored logical volumes on SAN.

Find out who does ifconfigs on servers. erasent ?

Migrate pahrdb01, qeerdb01, qaerdb01 to boot from VIO disks.

Consolidated systems and storage inventory.

Do not rely completely on sendmail to send alerts. Have syslog send a trap for standard scripts.

Develop, test and implement Linux mksysb.

Report sudo aging

Research VMcontrol and Active memory expansion.

Move reporting tasks to a non-privileged user.

We need a script to parse vhost → vio server names.

Install a standard version of OpenSSL and OpenSSH

Migrate storage from 146G LUNs to 34G/102G LUNs for sehrdb01 and dehrdb99.

Implement a consolidated inventory of unix servers, model, ser number, storage, san allocated, used and location. We should use /var/adm/.information

Audit /etc/profile, /etc/environment, /root/.profile - change the “PATH” variable .

Remove sulog script - that is redundant as sudo rolled out.

Implement NOEXEC in sudo to prevent shell escapes from known commands like “vi”. ( For a very far future )

Install and maintain samhain for system files.

Re-write rpt_config.sh as a generic one.

Install latest cfg2html versions for hpux AIX redhat SuSE CentOS

Modify / Re-write dr.sh

Improve VG creation.

Improve filesystem creation.

Simplify the script.

Eliminate the need for rsh for BCV backups. ( PTA TA2 ). Examine .rhosts for root on all servers.

Too many cron jobs on servers …. Standardize and remove the unwanted. Consolidate some of the housekeeping jobs.

Implement a documentation site on the Interexion data-centre and rsync the contents.

Document and display all physical servers and their network ports

Document all unix users and groups in one page and the command to re-create them if required.

Turn off sendmail from all servers.

taitc118 NIM server's network is kind of a mess. Fix it .

On AIX, make sure we have ssh started right after TCP/IP so that we can turn off telnet.

VIO server's /etc/profile is to be tuned.

Implement historical data display on Lpar documentation.

Implement the new UCRT summary page and new cfg2html. Write a new one using the allhosts file.

Write a lsdiskcfg equivalent to VIO networking configuration.

/prod/images/scripts to be the master copy of all shell scripts. Install a revision control system and manage the versions that way.

Scripts to modify and how

Work on the Redhat repository and replace them with the default one cobbler installed.

Modify /usr/local/scripts/stales.sh

Send email for HPUX as well.

Use sendmail with correct return path.

Done List

Figure out the unused disks on taitc103. Removed, 12 Raid1 disks returned to GIOS Storage Team.

Write up patching procedure for Redhat - do it once.

Test the redhat upgrade process. - Use paavap02 - install with 6.2 and upgrade to 6.3 - This is not possible, find an alternative.

Research and integrate Bladecentres in HMC.

Migrate paitap01 → paitap02 and move pablsv02 to the HS21 blade.

SNMP configuration

Solaris 8

AIX

Make sure rsyslog is correctly configured to goto unixlogs on all servers.

Bladecentre SAN switch upgrades.

Move the lpar2rrd workload from qehrdb01 to penmsv01.

Fix mksysb on all servers and standardize the script

Fix NTP and standardize configuration.

Have a script that checks for printQs status and enable them if found down & pingable [ Logit ].

Maintain a unix hosts database.

House keep /var/adm/wtmp if it grows more than 100Meg.

Document server decomm procedure.

Document server rename procedure.

New AIX/VIOS installs needs sysinter service enabled.

Make sure the special dr.sh on all VIO servers.

Install a temporary NIM server at Interexion.

penmsv01 - 10.56.1.*
penmsv01bck - 10.56.12.*

Document the I/O relationship between VIOS and guests

Find root cause of tasew007/8 Permanent Hardware errors on hdisks from Clariion. ( Moon has to unmap the VCM device )

LPAR2RRD error on taprvio6, taprvio15,18 etc

Consolidate the create alt_disk_copy script

NIM Investigate tftpboot time. ( Tweak in place )

Update getconsole database

Re-build pablsv01 as pglgsv01.

Migrate /edipro /patches /taediarch from tedv2e01's rootvg.

Migrate dggtdb01 to vio60/70.

Add a wiki page for all SAN storage for all systems.

Consolidate exclude.rootvg

Modify post install steps to support Redhat installations.

Migrate boot disks to R5 taprvio18,peerap09

Deploy the new mksysb-dr script.

Modify the mksysb script not to rely on hosts file Probably the best idea is to have it on /var/adm/.information file.

Housekeep /var/adm/wtmp

Point NTP configuration to these network devices.10.1.1.1,10.1.1.2,10.56.0.10 and 10.56.0.11

Modify lsdiskcfg to include pvids.

Run lsvpcfg.sh on all SAN connected servers and push data to wiki in a searchable format.

Implement a lsvpcfg.sh for MPIO. May be we need SYMCLI on all SAN connected servers.

Setup a housekeeping job to remove files older than 7 days from /var/spool/lpd/qdir and /var/spool/qdaemon.

LOCK DOWN itocroot OR replace with sudo.

Implement /var/adm/.information file on all servers and add it to the documentation.

Setup a ddir job for logfiles like “wtmp”.

Document blades, servers, locations and lpars.

taitc108 - dvds VG Removed VG and returned three 34 GB disks to GIOS Storage Team

Documented Disaster Recovery Servers Non Roorvg Volume Group Disk use

- Modify / Re-write dr.sh

Add AIO information. Done in time for 2013 D.R. Test. distributed to all servers. - Done - in dr.sh - Chris

AIX Commands for Splitting Vouume Group for Clone

Pay ATTENTION here⇒> On the server you are going to clone (the SOURCE server) to an lspv

 sudo lspv 

and record the output. You wlil need this later Don't loose it.

Determine number of disks required for the volume group you are going to cone and split and submit a ticket to the (at this time Gios Storage Team) requesting the disks you will need and ask they be assigned to the server. If the system you are cloning is a VIOS Client the disks will be assigned to the VIO Server for that client. Make sure you properly assign them to the correct VIOS Client system before you proceed.

Once you have the disks on the server you will be cloning another lapv to document capture the new disks.

 sudo lapv 

and again record the output. Do Not Loose this You will need it later.

Extend the volume group or groups you are going to clone with the new disks

Mirror the volume group to the new disks

sudo mirrorvg -c2 {insert volume group here} {insert list of new disks here} 

you can track it

while true
do
echo `date`
ps -aef | grep -v grep | grep mirror
ps -aef | grep -v grep | grep lresynclv -l
echo ""
sleep 60
done

When mirror has cuccessfully completed spit the vilume group

sudo splitvg -y {newvg} -c2 -i {original vg}

example: sudo splitvg -y datavg02 -c2 -i datavg01

Unmount the file systems from the cloned {newvg} volume group, in the example it would be datavg02

 for FS in `lsvgfs $VG | sort -r`
do
sudo umount $FS
wait
done

Varyoff the vouimme group(s)

sudo varyoffvg datavg02

Export the volume group

 sudo exportvg datavg02 

Give list of PVIDs from the added disks you caputed in step 3 above to GIOS Storage Member so they can “remove” them form the source server and assign them to the destination server.

The Followint are done on the TARGET /destination server

Do lspv and caprure output

 sudo lapv 

This captured all existing disks. Save this you will need it later

Run cfvmgr -v to bring disks onto server

 sudo cfgmgr -v

Rrun lspv and caprute to record all new disks

 lspv 

This caprutes an disks including disks just imported via cgfmgr. Save this you will need it later

Change Round -Robin and Reserver Lock Ploicies

 sudo chdev -l hdisk15 -a algorithm=round_robin -a rese rve_policy=no_reserve 

 sudo chdev -l hdisk15 -a algorithm=round_robin -a rese rve_policy=no_reserve 

Import the volume goups using pvids captured above pvids

mportvg -y binvg01 00f81260b60c614e

 importvg -y datavg01 00f81260b60d0e9

Run FSCK on each newly imported file systems #<># DO NOT PANIC The errors are expected #<>#

 for fs in $(lsvgfs binvg01)
     do
     sudo fsck -y $fs &
     done 

Remove the ”/fs” that is placed in front of file system names by the splitvg command, make directories, and mount

 for fs in $(lsvgfs binvg01 |sort )
     do
        newfs=$(echo ${fs} | sed "s;/fs;;g")
        sudo chfs -m $newfs $fs
        sudo mkdir -p $newfs
        sudo mount $newfs
     done 

 df -g

and mount

 for fs in $(lsvgfs datavg01 |sort )    
     do
        newfs=$(echo ${fs} | sed "s;/fs;;g")
        sudo chfs -m $newfs $fs
        sudo mkdir -p $newfs
        sudo mount $newfs
     done 

Create any additional file systems as required #<># Hint use /usr/local/scripts/filesystems.txt all the code and sizes are in there #<>#

Copy file systems from source server to this destinaton. #<># Remember t0 use the “x” and always rember to put in the trailing /

sudo rsync -axvv /usr/sap/put/ sehrdb01:/usr/sap/put/

SUDO Documentation for Users

sudo or as I call it “Super User Do” is a unix program that allows non-privileged users to execute some commands as root. sudo provides a rich set of features including monitoring, managing and alerting as compared to its competitors like setuid, proprietory RBAC or root equivalent user.

At Tenneco, we have identified the following teams as the ones who will need to run some programs as root.

DBA Team

Data preservation Team

SAP - Basis Team

HP Openview Team.

We need to group servers

Production Servers

Non production servers

Backup servers

Others

Usage

This is the easiest part. This is as simple as “prefix the command that you need to run as root with sudo”.

sudo /oracle/SID/11203/root.sh

The above command runs as root.

Dos & Don't(s)

There is no perfect security model. So there are ways around to break anything. May be, we should shutdown the OS, disconnect all cables, hide it, and kill the person who hid it. Even then there is still a chance. So is sudo, there are ways around and the methods are easily accessible.

Be responsible. sudo gives great power on a Unix system. “With great power comes great responsibility, visibility and publicity”. Think before you hit enter on that command that you prefixed with sudo.

Use sudo only when it really needed. It is not to be used for convenience. Do not fix a problem by “chmod 777” because you have the ability to do so for example.

Implementation Phase 1 ( Nov 24th 2012 )

Send communication to all GIOS users (OV, DBA, BASIS, Data proservation, Middleware).

Enter change event for Nov 24th.

Disable itocroot on all servers.

Team members of the above teams will have the ability to run any command as root on all non-production unix servers.

Unlimited sudo access for Data preservation team on all backup servers.

Unix team will keep a close watch on Usage of sudo and make recommendations on best practices.

Unix team will also learn patterns of sudo usage by various teams.

Implementation Phase 2 ( Jan - 2013 )

By this time Unix team will come up with a properly fine tuned set of root commands for each team.

Unix team will implement a new set of sudo rules that will rule out the need for a completely open sudo configuration. Individual teams will have the ability to run authorized programs as root using sudo.

Management and ongoing Maintenance

New projects, new applications OR new teams will need configuration changes to be made on sudo rules.

Unix team will perform these sudo rule's management as part of the project.

sudo rules will be maintained centrally, there will be no local changes allowed. By design, the local rules will be over written.

Limitations of sudo

Redirection is one limitation of sudo. i.e.

sudo echo "something" > /etc/motd

For security reasons, sudo does not permit re-directions. Instead, this works

echo "something" | sudo tee -a /etc/motd

“cd” command i.e.

sudo cd /protected-directory

This will not work. Instead use

sudo ls -l /protected-directory

Decommission Unix servers

Steps to do prior

Document all approvals from business, customers or other teams necessary.

Discuss within the team and get an agreement.

Create a Standard change control, get approval and do all the necessary paperwork.

Decommission - Day 1

Communicate with all stake holders that the server and it's apps are being decommissioned.

Have the application team stop all apps on the server

If backups required, please ask DataPres team to backup the server with requested retention period.

DRiV & Tenneco Servers follow the below steps and inform the team about the decommission

Send an email to Monitoring team to stop monitoring.

Send an email to Netbackup team to stop backing up the server.

Decommission - Day 2

Make sure the backups are completed. It could be a day or two.

Unmount & remove NFS mounts from clients when necessary and unexport the filesytems.

Shutdown the server

Remove The host from New Ansible tool. Follow the link Managing Hosts in Ansible provisioning tool

Decommission - Day 9

Return the SAN storage after clearing PVIDs and destroying the VGDA.

If this is a physical server,

Send a ticket for cables reclamation and any storage zones etc to delete.

Remove CDs/Tape media from the server.

Unrack the server or pull out the blade.

DRiV servers

Remove the host from pcdcunxaxap01:/prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console

Remove the host from pcdcunxaxap01:/prod/images/nimserver-utilities/Disaster.Recovery.List

Remove the host from pcdcunxaxap01:/prod/images/nimserver-utilities/Disaster.Recovery.List

Remove the host from PowerVM monitoring / LPAR2RRD - pcdcunxlxap02.

Remove the mksysb backup files pcdcunxaxap01.

Remove from NIM definitions pcdcunxaxap01.

Tenneco servers

Remove the host from pgnmsv01:/prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console

Remove the host from pgnmsv01:/prod/images/nimserver-utilities/Disaster.Recovery.List

Remove the host from penmsv01:/prod/images/nimserver-utilities/Disaster.Recovery.List

Remove the host from PowerVM monitoring / LPAR2RRD.

Remove the mksysb backup files.

Remove from NIM definitions.

Remove the LPAR/Blade/Frame as applicable.

Remove the HMC/ILO network/VMWare as applicable.

Request to remove from hardware maintenance. Email System model number and serial number to Robert - Not applicable if you are decommissioning .

Send ticket to reclaim DNS names, IP addresses, network ports and cables to Network team.

Goto service now and change the hardware status to retire for that server.

Goto service now and search for server –> Click option All —> then in the name column type the decommissioning server

Once you get the server change the status of the server to retire.